Finding Aid for Fox Island Lighthouse Association records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Fox Island Lighthouse Association records 1875-2012
Fox Island Lighthouse Association.
2013064 Bp 2 Aa3
The Fox Island Lighthouse Association is a non-profit organization founded to preserve the South Fox Island light station in northern Lake Michigan. The collection contains both paper and digital records, and consists of materials created or collected by the association as part of their efforts to preserve the light station.
0.4 linear feet
2.4 GB online
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by the Association (donor no. 10894 ) in 2013.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Fox Island Lighthouse Association (FILA) is a Traverse City, Michigan, non-profit organization (501(c)(3)) founded in 2004 by Sandy Bradshaw, John McKinney and Hans Joerg Rothenberger. Their goal was to rekindle the efforts of former groups for rescuing the South Fox Island light station, which had been abandoned in 1959 and has been threatened by gradual decay ever since. South Fox Island is in northern Lake Michigan, about 25 miles north of Leland, Michigan.
The South Fox Island Light Station was active for 101 years, from 1867 to 1968. The first lighthouse was a square light tower attached with an attached keeper's dwelling. In the 1890s, a separate dwelling space for assistant lighthouse keepers was built as well as a fog signal building and other structures. A new, brick assistant keepers' dwelling was built in 1910. In 1934, a new light tower, a skeletal tower taken from Sapelo Island, Georgia, was installed. The light station became automated in 1958 and the last light keeper left the island. The light station was decommissioned in 1968 due to improvements in ships' onboard navigation equipment.
In 1971 the U.S. Department of the Interior transferred 115 acres of land on the southern tip of South Fox Island (excepting the light station buildings and grounds) to the State of Michigan Department of Natural Resources for public use. In 1980, the light station buildings and grounds were also deeded to the State of Michigan.
Until the establishment of the Fox Island Lighthouse Association, few efforts had been made toward the upkeep of the property. One exception was work done in summer 1984 by Michigan Youth Corps members under direction from the Traverse Bay Area Intermediate School District Youth Employment Services. In 2002, the Fox Island Education Association (FIEA) was founded but later disbanded. Two years later, the South Fox Island Lighthouse Restoration Project (SFILRP) was founded by two former FIEA members, Sandy Bradshaw and John McKinney, along with Hans Joerg Rothenberger. SFILRP was renamed Fox Island Lighthouse Association (FILA) in 2005. It gained non-profit status in 2006 and work began on the island later that year. Since then, FILA volunteers have made significant progress in improving the condition of the light station grounds and buildings. A Historic Structure Report, completed in 2011 by U.P. Engineers & Architects and submitted to the State Historical Preservation Office, now guides the restoration and construction work.
The collection contains both paper and digital records, and consists of materials created or collected by the Fox Island Lighthouse Association as part of their efforts to preserve the South Fox Island light station. Collected material includes copies of U.S. Lighthouse Service and Coast Guard records from the National Archives, including photographs. The collection also includes the association's newsletters, newspaper articles about the association or the light station, a historic structures report developed for the association by U.P. Engineers & Architects, and a series of oral history interviews of former lighthouse personnel, conducted by association members.
The Fox Island Lighthouse Association records are organized into four series: Organizational Records, Collected Research Materials, Oral Histories, and Visual Materials. All but the Visual Materials series contain both print and digital records, and some documents exist in both formats.
Subjects:
Fox Island Lighthouse Association.; Lighthouses--Michigan--Conservation and restoration.; South Fox Island Light Station (Mich.); South Fox Island (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Fox Island Lighthouse Association.; Conservation & restoration.; Lighthouses--Michigan.; South Fox Island Light Station (Mich.); South Fox Island (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Digital images.; Maps (documents); Oral histories.; Photographs.
- Organizational Records 1978-2012 2004-2012
  The Organizational Records series (4 folders and 736 MB, 1978-2012) consists of materials documenting or supporting the work of the organization, both on and off the island. This includes copies of FILA newsletters, presentation files, fact sheets about the island and its buildings, and the Historic Structure Report prepared by U.P. Engineers and Architects (which provides a history of the light station in addition to descriptions and recommendations for its buildings and structures) as well as collected news articles about the organization's work and the history of the light station.
  - FILA non-profit information: Information sheets, presentation files, newsletters, and other materials
    - Brochure, restoration notes, and award program 2004-2011 (Box 1)
    - Collage, task list, and captain's log, circa 2009, .ZIP file
    - Information sheets on buildings with images, circa 2010, .ZIP file
    - Michigan Waterways Commission Presentation files including photos 2010, .ZIP file
    - Newsletters 2008-2012 (Box 1)
    - Newsletters 2009-2011, .ZIP file
    - Notes for FILA spring 2012 newsletter, .ZIP file
  - Historic Structure Report for South Fox Island Light Station
    - Administrative materials, architectural diagrams and plans, images, and feedback 2010-2012 (Box 1)
    - Final report November 30, 2011, .ZIP file
  - Collected news articles and other Fox Island information
    - News releases/notes and clippings 1978-2012 (Box 1)
    - News articles and other materials, .ZIP file
      - News articles, brochures, and other documents 1983, circa 2010-2011
      - News articles, fact sheet, and other documents, circa 2009
      - News article, circa 2010
      - News article and welcome sheet, circa 2011
- Collected Research Materials 1875-1971, 2009-2010
  The Collected Research Materials series (3 folders and 786 MB, 1875-1971 and 2009-2010) contains copies of photographs, maps, diagrams, correspondence, and other documents gathered in researching the history of the light station, its inhabitants, and its structures. Much of the material was copied or scanned at the National Archives in Chicago. It includes records from the U.S. Coast Guard and U.S. Lighthouse Service as well as material about or from the lighthouse keepers themselves.
  - U.S. Coast Guard
    - Administrative records, diagrams, and photographs 1907-1971 (Box 1)
    - Photographs (scanned, 2012) of island and structures 1960s, .ZIP file
  - U.S. Lighthouse Service
    - Records, maps, and additional correspondence 1884-1907, undated (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, log book pages, and other items 1875-1895, .PDF file and .ZIP file
    - Correspondence
      - Engineer or Naval Secretary to the Engineer of the 9th Light-House District 1891-1904, .PDF file and .ZIP file (Box 1)
      - Lighthouse Board to the Lighthouse Inspector 1887-1907, .PDF file and .ZIP file (Box 1)
      - Lighthouse Inspector to the Lighthouse Keeper or Assistant Keeper 1891-1905, .PDF file and .ZIP file (Box 1)
      - Lighthouse Keeper or Assistant Keeper to Lighthouse Inspector 1891, 1897-1906, .PDF file and .ZIP file (Box 1)
  - Lighthouse keepers' material, personnel information, photographs, diagrams, and maps 1884, 1907, 2010, undated (Box 1)
- Oral Histories 1953, 2009-2011
  The Oral Histories series (8 folders and 496 MB, 1953 and 2009-2011) includes materials documenting oral history interviews with individuals who worked or lived at the South Fox Island Light Station while it was in operation. Interviewees include:
  James Alger and Paul Stephan, who both served in the U.S. Coast Guard at Clarlevoix in the mid-1950s and helped transfer people and goods from the mainland to various light stations, including the one on South Fox Island
  Zane Bourisseau, who spent summers on the island as a child with his father, Frank Bourisseau, who was an assistant lightkeeper from 1928-1937
  Robert [Bob] Harris, who served as an engineer at the South Fox Island light station in 1953, and his wife, Rheda
  Robert June, who served on South Fox Island in 1955 and 1956 as part of the U.S. Coast Guard, and his wife, Betty
  David Markle, who served on South Fox Island as part of the U.S. Coast Guard for one season, in 1957, and his wife Audrey.
  The interviews serve to document the features of the island and its structures as well as stories of life on the island in the early to mid-twentieth century. The level of documentation varies by interview but may include audio files, transcripts, interview notes, summaries, diagrams, photographs, and copies of related correspondence.
  - "Agreement on use" form 2011, .ZIP file
  - Alger, James: interviewed by John Wells October 26, 2010
    - Audio recording and transcript 2010, .ZIP file
    - Notes, transcript, and correspondence 2010-2011 (Box 1)
  - Bourisseau, Zane: interviewed by Carla Woodcock of the Lake County Historical Society August 17, 2011
    - Audio recording 2011, .ZIP file
    - Summary, notes, and correspondence 2011 (Box 1)
  - Harris, Robert (Bob) and Rheda: interviewed by Jan Beller and Linda Baron April 14, 2010
    - Summary of interview 2010, .ZIP file
    - Photographs, summary, correspondence, and diagrams 1953, 2010-2011 (Box 1)
  - June, Betty interviewed by Karen Wells January 27, 2011
    - Transcript 2011, .ZIP file (Box 1)
  - June, Robert interviewed by John Wells January 27, 2011
    - Audio recording and transcript 2011, .ZIP file
    - Notes, transcript, and correspondence 2011 (Box 1)
  - Markle, David Edward August 16, 2009
    - Notes from Interview 2009 (Box 1)
    - Interview transcript 2009, .ZIP file (Box 1)
    - Partial transcript of visit to the island with wife (Audrey Markle) circa 2009, .ZIP file
  - Stephan, Paul and James Alger, interviewed by John Wells October 26, 2010
    - Transcript and correspondence 2010 (Box 1)
    - Audio recording and transcript 2010, .ZIP file
- Visual Materials 1980s, 2006-2010
  The Visual Materials series (462 MB, 1980s and 2006-2010) contains digital images of the island, FILA volunteers, and their work. Most of the images are digital photographs, but some maps are also included. The series is organized into 4 parts by the subject of the images: General, Island structures and grounds, Volunteers, and Miscellaneous. General includes sets of images documenting the island overall, such as web cam images and aerial photographs. Island structures and grounds documents the various buildings and other structures on the island, particularly before and after a restoration or repair project. Volunteers includes digital photographs of FILA volunteers on the island or the water, often working on various projects. Miscellaneous consists of digital photographs of a red dinghy and a boat sunk off shore.
  - General
    - Aerial photographs of South Fox Island and structures 2006, undated, .ZIP file
    - Maps of South Fox and Michigan (with one scanned photograph of "winter on the island") undated, .ZIP file
    - Visit by Grace Johnson (Michigan mapmaker and photographer): photographs of the island, structures, and people 1980s, .ZIP file
    - Web cam images of island, water, and buildings in the snow
      - December 2008, .ZIP file
      - Ca. 2010, .ZIP file
  - Island structures and grounds, .ZIP file
    - Assistant keepers' quarters interior and exterior 2006-2007, undated
    - Boat house interior and exterior 2006-2009
    - Carpenter's shop exterior 2006-2009, undated
    - Dock, lake, and shoreline 2009, undated
    - Fog Signal Building interior and exterior 2007, 2009, undated
    - Lighthouse (1867) interior and exterior 2006-2009, undated
    - Oil house exterior 2007, undated
    - Skeletal lighthouse tower 2006-2007, undated
    - Walkways overgrown and cleared 2007, 2009, undated
  - Volunteers
    - "Team Spears" working on the island dock 2009, .ZIP file
    - Volunteers working on projects 2006-2009, undated, .ZIP file
    - Volunteers on the water and island, working, eating, etc. 2010, .ZIP file
  - Miscellaneous, .ZIP file
    - Red Dinghy on the water and on the shore 2006, undated
    - Sunk boat in the lake undated